Guide to the George Roy Hill Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Roy Hill papers
1968-1982
MS 1765
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
249.25
(197 boxes)
The papers consist largely of motion picture film used in the production of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid and Slaughterhouse-Five. Additional materials include the production files, action photographs, and story boards from Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, as well as interviews and other documentation used for the documentary The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid.
Hill, George Roy, 1921-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Media Design Studio, Yale University, 1980 and 1982, and from Universal Studios in 1986, 1987, and 1989. Additional material added in 2003.
Custodial History
Originally part of YRG 20-H.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Separated Materials
Three oversize mounted photographic prints of still images from the film Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid were removed from the collection.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one addition: I. Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid Production Files, Circa 1968-1971. Series II. Slaughterhouse-Five Files, Circa 1972. Series III. The World According to Garp Files, Circa 1981-1982.
Biographical / Historical
George Roy Hill was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota, in 1922 to George R. and Helen Frances Hill. After receiving his B.A. degree in music from Yale University in 1943, he served two years in the Marine Corps as a transport plane pilot. In 1949, Hill received a B.Litt. in literature and music from Trinity College, Dublin, and made his acting debut with Cyril Cusack at the Abbey Theatre in London. Hill's first teleplay, My Brother's Keeper, was presented in 1953 on the Kraft Television Theater. In 1956, Hill produced, directed, and co-authored A Night to Remember, for which he received two Emmy award nominations (for directing and writing); during the next six years, Hill continued to produce and direct presentations for television. Hill's directorial debut was the 1962 adaptation of Tennessee Williams's Period of Adjustment. Between 1962-1988, Hill directed thirteen additional films including Hawaii (1966), Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid (1969), Slaughterhouse-Five (1972), and The Sting(1973), for which he was awarded the Oscar for best director.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist largely of motion picture film used in the production of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid and Slaughterhouse-Five. Additional materials include the production files, action photographs, and story boards from Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid, as well as interviews and other documentation used for the documentary The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid.
Motion pictures; Hill, George Roy, 1921-2002
- Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid Files, Circa 1967-1971; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid series consists of two subseries of production files related to the creation of the movie Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid and of film footage and interviews used in the production of the documentary film, Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid. The bulk of the material are film reels, correspondence, working and final scripts, material on prospective actors, film stills, and storyboards-both photographic and "cut-to" drawings.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Order Reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives website.
  Arrangement
  The Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid series is organized alphabetically.
  - Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid movie, 1967-1971
    The Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid subseries contains material that relates directly to the production of the feature film Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid such as photographs, costume designs, set design and blueprints, models, and storyboards, as well as correspondence with George Roy Hill, William Goldman, and various Hollywood executives.
    - Correspondence and interviews, 1968-1971
      - Actors correspondence and interviews, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      - Camera shot details correspondence (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Freebain, Tom to Dean Howard Weaver, Yale-related correspondence, 1971 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Goldman, William and Hollywood executives, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hill, George Roy correspondence (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Hill, George Roy taped interview, 1969 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Location correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Premiere of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Promotion correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Schedule correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Staff and crew lists, script correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Films, circa 1968
      - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 1, Circa 1968; 1 (Box 2)
      - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 3, Circa 1968; 1 (Box 3)
      - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 6, Circa 1968; 1 (Box 4)
      - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 9, Circa 1968; 1 (Box 5)
    - Photographs, circa 1968
      - Action shot, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Action scene, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Beach scenes, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Burnt out train, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Butch Cassidy, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Benson, Lula (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Carnival scene, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Carnival scenes, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Car show scenes, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Cast on set, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Cinema scene, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Color shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
      - Concordia mines, Bolivia, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Establishing shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Etta Place still, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - George Roy Hill with actors on set, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - George Roy Hill on set, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - George Parker and Harry Longsbaugh (Butch and the Sundance Kid), circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Group shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Historical shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Horse and carriage shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Horseless carriage scenes, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Indoor shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Indoor vehicle shots, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Jewelry store scene, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Jewelry store scenes, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Katharine Ross, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Movie scene, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Movie stills, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Negatives, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
      - Newman and Redford, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Newman and Ross in swimsuits/beach clothes, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - New York scenes, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Outdoor scenes with carriage and horses, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Outdoor and park scenes, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Outdoor street scenes and tailor shop, circa 1968 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Party scenes, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Party scenes, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Paul Newman, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Paul Newman, Robert Redford, Katharine Ross and Barbara Stanwyck in various combinations, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Photography studio scene, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Posse in pursuit, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Promo shots of Newman and Redford, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Robert Redford, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Robert Redford on set, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Scene breakdown, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Shots of people lying on the ground, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Shots of people in spectator boxes, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Studio rehearsal, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Studio shot photographs, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Studio shot re-creations, circa 1968 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - The Sundance Kid and Etta Place, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - The Sundance Kid, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Train car scene, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Train station, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Train scene, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Wild Bunch, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Production design, 1967-1969
      - Action storyboards, circa 1968 (Folder 12)
      - Agnes and Fanny Porter costume design, circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Apex and chase shooting plan, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Art and set lists, 1968 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Backdrop design illustration, circa 1968 (Folder 13)
      - Bank robbery storyboard, circa 1968 (Folder 14)
      - Budget, 1968 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Budget, 1968 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Budget detail for ladies wardrobe, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Butch Cassidy costume design, circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 2-6)
      - Butch speaking to the crowd scene layout, circa 1968 (Folder 15)
      - Camera shot details, circa 1968 (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
      - Call sheets and production reports, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Cameraman daily film report, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
      - Durango cast and crew lists, 1968 September 10 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Etta Place costume design, circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 7-9)
      - Etta's house model and diorama, circa 1968 (Box 16)
        This material cannot be accessed without archivist permission.
      - Etta's house specifications, circa 1968 (Folder 17)
      - Etta Place research, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Evan Lee Ranch Hole in the Wall set location shots, circa 1968 (Folder 18)
      - Establishing shots, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Exhibit displays, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
      - Film poster, circa 1969 (Folder 19–21)
      - Film stills, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Final production crossplot, circa 1968 (Folder 22)
      - Hill, George Roy notes, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Illustrated storyboard, circa 1968 (Folder 23)
      - Illustrated timeline and storyboard, circa 1968 (Folder 24)
      - John William Clouser wanted poster (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Labor and wardrobe preliminary budgets, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Location, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Main titles, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Media design blueprint, 1968 (Box 25)
      - Men's wardrobe budget details, circa 1968 (Folder 102)
      - Newspaper articles (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Newspaper articles (Folder 103)
      - New York scene design, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Oregon shooting schedule, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Preliminary production cost estimate, 1968 August 19 (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Previews, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Production sound report, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Promotional film stills, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Rapid jump design, circa 1968 (Folder 104)
      - Revised breakdown, 1968 August 14 (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - Revised pages of scripts, 1968 November (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Scene breakdown, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 6-9)
      - Scene breakdown script, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Scene cut storyboards, circa 1968 (Folder 105)
      - Scene design negatives, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 22)
      - Scene setup and design notes, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - Scene sketches, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Scene synopsis sketch, 1969 June 12 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Set design blueprints, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 25)
      - Set building specification, circa 1968 (Folder 106)
      - Set building specification, circa 1968 (Folder 107)
      - Shack model and diorama, circa 1968 (Box 108)
      - Shorthand notes, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 26)
      - Storyboard sketches, scenes 298-495, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 27)
      - Staff and crew lists, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 28)
      - Storyboard art, circa 1968 (Folder 109)
      - The Sundance Kid costume design, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 10-13)
      - Technical contracts and set photographs, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 29)
      - Tentative budgets, 1967 December 7 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Scripts and scores, 1968
      - Complete musical score and lyrics, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 31)
      - Critical notes, first cut, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 32)
      - Final screeplay, 1968 July 15 (Box 9, Folder 33)
      - Revised pages, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Script, final version, 1968 July 15 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      - Scripts, 1968 (Box 110, Folder 1-5)
  - The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid documentary, circa 1968-1969
    The The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid subseries contains primarily films from the making of the documentary The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid. The dates of the bulk of the material are estimated to be 1968.
    - A/B roll 10 minute versions logs, 1969 (Box 110, Folder 6)
    - A/B roll complete version logs, 1969 (Box 110, Folder 7)
    - Beginning of show 3-stripe magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 1 (Box 111)
    - CCP-making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid NBC TV version, circa 1968; 1 (Box 112)
    - Conni, circa 1968; 1 (Box 113)
    - Dialogue track 1 and 2 reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 114)
    - Dialogue track 1 reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 115)
    - Dialogue track 1 reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 116)
    - Dialogue track 1 reel 5, circa 1968; 1 (Box 117)
    - Dialogue track 2 reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 118)
    - Dialogue track 2 reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 119)
    - Dialogue track 2 reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 120)
    - Dialogue track 3 reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 121)
    - Dialogue track reel 4 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 122)
    - Effects 3 reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 123)
    - Effects track 1 reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 124)
    - Effects track 1 reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 125)
    - Effects track 1 reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 126)
    - Effects track 1 reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 127)
    - Effects track 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 128)
    - Effects track 2 reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 129)
    - Effects track 2 reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 130)
    - Effects track 2 reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 131)
    - Effects track 2 reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 132)
    - Effects tracks 1 and 2 reel 5, circa 1968; 1 (Box 133)
    - Element effects 3 reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 134)
    - George Roy Hill film and outtakes 1st narration 52 1/2, work print, circa 1968; 8 (Box 135)
    - George Roy Hill film narration part 52 2/2, circa 1968; 8 (Box 136)
    - Goldman 1st and 2nd and Gatsby full coat magnetic soundtrack reel, circa 1968; 1 (Box 137)
    - Goldman 2nd full coat magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 1 (Box 138)
    - Loop rolls, circa 1968; 17 (Box 139)
    - Mix II track reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 140)
    - Mix track 1 reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 141)
    - Mix track 2 reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 142)
    - Mix track reel 1, circa 1968; 1; 950 ft. long (Box 143)
    - Mix track reel 2, circa 1968; 1; 950 ft. long (Box 144)
    - Mix track reel 5, circa 1968; 1; 1050 ft. long (Box 145)
    - Narration with music, circa 1968; 1 (Box 146)
    - New York sequence reel, circa 1968; 1 (Box 147)
    - Newman interview part 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 148)
    - Newman interview short trims, circa 1968; 1 (Box 149)
    - Newman, Redford, Ross, Newman-Redford, circa 1968; 1 (Box 150)
    - Original 10 minute version A-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 151)
    - Original 10 minute version B-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 152)
    - Original picture R1 A-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 153)
    - Original picture R1 B-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 154)
    - Original pictures R2 A-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 155)
    - Original picture R2 B-roll, circa 1968; 1 (Box 156)
    - "Original soundtrack reel 1-2-3-4" full coat magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 1 (Box 157)
    - Original version reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 158)
    - Original version reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 159)
    - Original version reel 3, circa 1968; 1 (Box 160)
    - Original version reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 161)
    - Original version reel 5, circa 1968; 1 (Box 162)
    - Original work print reel 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 163)
    - Outtakes, circa 1968; 10 (Box 164)
    - Outtakes picture, circa 1968; 8 (Box 165)
    - Outtakes sound and picture bits magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 13 (Box 166)
    - Part 1 35/32 optical track negative, circa 1968; 1 (Box 167)
    - Part 2 35/32 optical track negative, circa 1968; 1 (Box 168)
    - Picture trims, circa 1968; 3 (Box 169)
    - Picture trims, circa 1968; 3 (Box 170)
    - Picture trims, circa 1968; 14 (Box 171)
    - R1 Dia 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 172)
    - Redford interview short trims, circa 1968; 1 (Box 173)
    - Redford interview, P-52 Redford, circa 1968; 1 (Box 174)
    - "Re-recorded track reel 4-5-6" full coat magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 1 (Box 175)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 176)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 4, circa 1968; 1 (Box 177)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 5, circa 1968; 1 (Box 178)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 7, circa 1968; 1 (Box 179)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 8, circa 1968; 1; 1000 ft. long (Box 180)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 10, circa 1968; 1 (Box 181)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 11, circa 1968; 1 (Box 182)
    - Second re-recorded left track sound reel 12, circa 1968; 1 (Box 183)
    - Soundtrack reels 5, 6, 7, 8 full coat magnetic soundtrack, circa 1968; 1 (Box 184)
    - Spanish lesson, Bank, Bloodbath reel, circa 1968; 1 (Box 185)
    - Tag part 1, circa 1968; 1 (Box 186)
    - Tag part 2 track, circa 1968; 1 (Box 187)
    - Tape trims, circa 1968; 7 (Box 188)
    - Tape trims, circa 1968; 16 (Box 189)
    - Tape trims, circa 1968; 9 (Box 190)
    - Teaser trims titles, circa 1968; 9 (Box 191)
    - Teaser trim titles, circa 1968; 3 (Box 192)
    - Teaser trims titles, circa 1968; 4 (Box 193)
    - Track trims - tent segments, circa 1968; 1 (Box 194)
    - Unlabeled reel, circa 1968; 1 (Box 195)
    - Work print part 2, circa 1968; 1 (Box 196)
    - Work print part original print narration, circa 1968; 1 (Box 197)
- Slaughterhouse-Five Files, Circa 1971-1973; Series II
  This series is comprised almost entirely of film footage and sound from the original production of Slaughterhouse-Five, as well as interviews of actors, George Roy Hill, and other production crew members that were used in the creation of a documentary about the making of the movie. The documentary was never released due to incomplete copyright clearances. However, the final workprints as well as several "teaser" trailers are included in the files. The remainder of the series is comprised of sketches of scenes by Gene Johnson, and a small group of black and white photographs from the making of the film.
  - Photographs (Box 26)
  - Sketches of scenes, by Gene Johnson (Box 27–28)
  - "Teaser" trailers, Workprint of documentary, film and sound in cans (Box 29–98)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- The World According to Garp Files, Circa 1981-1982; Series III
  This series contains material used in the production of the motion picture film, The World According to Garp (1982). Included are photographs, architectural drawings, and set designs.
  - Folio set of drawings (Box 15A)
    - Additional material (Box 15B)
    - Additional material (Box 15C)
  - Photographs, architectural drawings, and set designs (Box 99)
    - Additional material (Box 100)
    - Additional material (Box 101)
- Additional material, Circa 1971-1973; Accession 2004-M-013
  This accession contains film reels and documents relating to the films Slaughterhouse-Five (1972) and The Effect of Gamma Rays on Man-in-the-Moon Marigolds (1972). Unless otherwise indicated in the inventory below, collection materials are undated.
  - Slaughterhouse-Five
    Comprises approximately thirty-five reels of motion picture film in various sizes housed in ten boxes, some wound on cores and some not.
    - Trims (Box 1–4)
    - Sound (Box 5–6)
    - Picture and sound (Box 7–8)
    - Titles (Box 9–10)
  - Newman/Woodward Marigolds and Slaughterhouse-Five sound tapes, Approximately 80 audiotapes (reel-to-reel) (Box 11)
  - Still photographs from the film Slaughterhouse-Five, Circa 1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and notes relating to The Making of Butch Cassidy and the Sundance Kid and information on television documentaries, Circa 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 2)